Finding Aid for German Auxiliaries Muster Rolls
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- German Auxiliaries Muster Rolls, 1776-1786 (bulk 1781-1783)
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[hristian] V[on] Romrod, E[manuel] de Wilmowsky, [Conrad] Schraidt, C[arl Heinrich Friedrich] Lange, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 19. Located in Oversize Manuscripts (see below)
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[hristian] V[on] Romrod, E[manuel] de Wilmowsky, H[ieronimus] Berner, [Friedrich Wilhelm] Fey, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 20a. Located in Oversize Manuscripts (see below)
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. Charles de Kietzell, G. Langenschwartz, C[hristian] Münch, Jean Paul, and G[eorge] Langenschwartz DS, June 24, 1782, 20b. Located in Oversize Manuscripts (see below)
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. Charles de Kietzell, G. Langenschwartz, Lewis de Schallern, Guillaume Justi, J[ohann] P[hilipp Henri] Petri, and Henri Zilcher DS, June 24, 1782, 20c. Regiment d'Infanterie du Colonel De Seitz de la Compagnie du Lieutenant Colonel De Schallern pour 182. Jours du 25me. Decbr. 1781. jus'qu au 24me. Juin 1782 inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Charles de Kietzell, Maj. G. Langenschwartz, Lieut. Col. Lewis de Schallern, Lieut. Guillaume Justi, ensign Johann Philipp Henri Petri, and ensign Henri Zilcher. (Folder 27)
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. Charles de Kietzell, G. Langenschwartz, George Langenschwartz, C[arl] A[ugust] Vieth, Ludw[ig] Friedr[ich] v[on] Boineburg, and G. Christian Itter DS, June 24, 1782, 20d. Regiment d'Infanterie du Colonel de Seitz de la Compagnie du Major Langenschwartz pour 182 Jours du 25me December 1781 Jusqu'au 24me. Juin 1782 inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Charles de Kietzell, Maj. G. Langenschwartz, Capt. George Langenschwartz, 2nd Lieut. Carl August Vieth, 2nd Lieut. Ludwig Friederich von Boineburg, and ensign Christian Itter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. Charles de Kietzell, G. Langenschwartz, J[ean] Neuman, J[acob] W[ilhelm] Bode, Jean Knies, and E[manuel] Muuss DS, June 24, 1782, 20e. Regiment d Infanterie du Colonel de Seitz de la Compagnie du Major Neuman, pour 182 Jours du 25me. Decembr. 1781 jusqu'au 24me. Juin 1782, inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Charles de Kietzell, Maj. G. Langenschwartz, Maj. Jean Neuman, Capt. Lieut. Jacob Wilhelm Bode, 2nd Lieut. Jean Knies, and ensign Emanuel Muuss. (Folder 28)
  - [Hesse-Hanau]. G[eorg] Pausch and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 20, 1781, 21a. Muster Roll of the present Officers and Men, of a Detachement of His Serene Highness Prince of Hessen Hanau Artillery, as muster'd by His Britannick Majesty's Commissary Wm. Porter Esqr., at Brooklyn on Long Island July the 20. de. 1781.
  - [Hesse-Hanau, Jäger Corps]. G[eorg] Pausch and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 20, 1781, 21b. Muster Roll. of His Serene Highness Prince of Hesse Hanau Yager Recruits, sent over from Hanau in the year 1780, as mustre'd by His Britanick Majesty's Commissary of Muster, Wm. Porter Esqr., at Fort Brooklyn on Long-Island July the 20. 1781. (Folder 29)
  - [Waldeck. 3rd Regiment]. C[hristoffle] Alberti, G. de Haacke, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 12, 1782, 22. Muster Roll of Captain Albertis Compy: of the 3d. Regiment of Waldeck, for 182 Days, from the 25th. Decbr 1781 to the 24th. June 1782... Signed by Captain Christoffle Alberti, Captain G. de Haacke, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Waldeck. 3rd Regiment]. C[hristoffle] Alberti, Keppel, and Nolting 2 DS Fragments, August 24, 1778, 23. Two fragments of muster rolls. Each concluded: Passe'en Revue la Susdite Compagnie du Troissieme Regiment de Waldeck, Savoir le Capitaine et Son Garçon, un Premier Lieutenant et Son garçon, un Enseigne et Son Garçon, trois Sergeants, un Fourier, un Capit: d'armes, un Chirurgien, Six Caporaux, deux Tambours, et quatre vingt dix et un Soldats ÿ compris le Solliciteur, le tout duement et complettement armé. Both signed by Capt. C. Alberti, Lieut. Keppel, and ensign Nolting. (Folder 30)
  - [Waldeck. 3rd Regiment]. Augustin Alberti, G. de Haacke, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 12, 1782, 24. Muster Roll of Lieut. Colonel and Capt. De Horns Company of the 3d. Regiment of Waldeck for 182 Days, from the 25 of Decembr 1781 to the 24 of June 1782... Signed by Capt. Lieut. Augustin Alberti, Capt. G. de Haacke, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Waldeck. 3rd Regiment]. C. De Horn, W[ilhelm] Keppel, C[arl] Hohmann, Lud[wig] Schmid[t], C[arl] Müller, and W[illiam] Porter DS, June 24, 1782, 25a. Major Penzels Compagnie [3rd Regiment of Waldeck]. Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781 to June 24, 1782. Signed by 1st Lieut. Wilhelm Keppel, 2nd Lieut. Carl Hohmann, ensign Ludwig Schmidt, ensign Carl Müller, Lieut. Col. Albrecht De Horn, and commissary William Porter. (Folder 31)
  - [Waldeck. 3rd Regiment]. A[lbrecht] De Horn, A[lexander] de Baumbach, F[riedr.] de Wilmowsky, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 12, 1782, 25b. Muster Roll of the Vacant Company, of the 3d Regiment of Waldeck, for 182 Days from the 25th. Of Decbr 1781. to the 24th. June 1782... Signed by Lieut. Col. Albrecht De Horn; Capt. Lieut. Alexander de Baumbach; Lieut. Friedr. de Wilmowsky, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Brunswick]. Gebhard Partially Printed DS, March 9, 1779, 26. T. F. Gebhard, Lieutenant and Pay Master of the Grenadier Bataillon de Mengen, signed this partially printed document for the receipt of 871/2/2 subsistence money for a body of Brunswick troops, held prisoner in the Province of Massachusetts Bay. Imprint beginning "RECEIVED of DAVID THOMAS, Esq; Deputy-Paymaster of His Majesty's Forces in North-America," Docket: "Expedition to Rhode Island." (Folder 32)
  - [Brunswick and Great Britain]. William Faucit and J. B. von Feronce DS Copy, January 9, 1776, 27. Tractal. Zwischen Sr. Grossbrittanischen Majestat und dem regierenden Herzoge von Braunschweig Unterzeichnet Braunschweig d. 9 Januar 1776. Handwritten copy of the treaty between Great Britain and the Duke of Brunswick, providing for the use of Brunswick troops against the Americans.
  - [Anspach]. de Reitzenstein, Henry Model, and Anthony Morengill DS, March 16, 1778, 28. Account of Reparations in the Quarters of the first Regiment of the Anspachs Troops, during winter quarters from 1777 to 1778. Signed by Maj. de Reitzenstein and Quartermaster Maj. Henry Model. Docket: "Barrack Account of the first Regt. Of Anspach Troops." (Folder 33)
  - [Anspach]. Christoph von Waldenfels Partially Printed DS, July 13, 1779, 29. Receipt on acount of subsistence for a Corps of Anspach Chasseurs. Signed by Captain Christoph von Waldenfels. Imprint beginning: "RECEIVED from THOMAS BARROW, Esq; Deputy of the Paymaster General of His Majesty's Forces."
  - [Brunswick]. H. Cleve LS, August 1782, 30. Sending enclosed papers [not present] to an unidentified Lord, at the request of the Duke of Brunswick and Brunswick Minister of State Feronce Baron de Rotencreutz. "Your Lordeship would be pleased, to give necessary Orders for their further Safety." (Folder 34)
  - Victualling Office Commissioners. J[ohn] Slade, A[lexander] Chorley, and G[eorge] P[hilipps] Towry LS to Rich[ar]d Rigby, May 24, 1786, 31. Discussing accounts made out by the Victualling Office for foreign troops aboard British ships of war and transports. Inability to distinguish troops of the Landgrave of Hesse from those of Hesse-Hanau, on account of not receiving such a distinction in the lists from the ships' pursors.
  - Victualling Office Commissioners. Geo[rge] Cherry, A[lexander] Chorley, G[eorge] P[hilipps] Towry, W[illia]m Lance, and W[illiam] Boscawen LS to [Richard] Rigby, December 13, 1786, 32. Respecting the settlement of accounts pertinent to shipboard stoppages during the late war, for the victualling of soldiers, women, and children in multiple regiments. Signed by George Cherry, Alexander Chorley, George Philipps Towry, William Lance, and William Boscawen. (Folder 35)
  - Victualling Office Commissioners. Geo[rge] Cherry, J[ames] Kirke, and G[eorge] P[hilipps] Towry LS to [William Grenville, 1st Baron] Grenville and [Constantine Phipps, 2nd Baron] Mulgrave, November 8, 1786, 33. Letter to the Paymasters of the Forces respecting the settlement of accounts pertinent to shipboard stoppages during the late war, for the victualling of soldiers, women, and children in multiple regiments. Signed by George Cherry, James Kirke, and George Philipps Towry
  - W[illiam] Porter ALS to [William Petty, 1st Marquess of Lansdowne, 2nd Earl of] Shelburne, August 5, 1782, with 9 enclosures, 34. Located in Oversize Manuscripts (see below)
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. Th[oma]s Carleton DS, [1780], 35. Distribution De l'Argent de Bagage & Batt & 200 Jours, Argent de Fourages pour les Regiment, d Kniphausen [Knyphausen] pour L'Anné 1780. Signed by Quartermaster General Thomas Carleton. (Folder 36)
  - [Hesse Cassel]. Tho[ma]s Gamble and Tho[ma]s Carleton DS, [1781], 36. Distribution des 200 Jours Argent de Fourages Bagage Et Batt, pour les Regiment Hessois de Son Excellence Le Lieutenant General Kniphausen [Knyphausen] pour 1781. [With] Distribution des... Argent de Fourage Bagage Et Batt pour le Regiment Hessois de Son Excellence le Lieutenant General D'Lossberg, pour L'Anné 1781. [With] Distribution des 165 Jours Argent de Fourage pour le Regiment Hessois de Son Excellence le Lieutenant d'Kniphausen pour L'Anné 1781. Signed by Thomas Gamble and Quartermaster General Thomas Carleton. (Folder 37)
  - Payments on Account of the Foreign Troops in General... Document, [after July 1783, regarding accounts June 1, 1776-July 28, 1783], The following Payments on Account of the Foreign Troops in General have been Extracted from the American Extraordinaries. Includes accounts marked Quebec, Montreal, New York, Convention Army, and Rhode Island.
  - [Friedrich Adolph, Freiherr von] Riedesel DS, September 13, 1779, Voucher for Subsistence on Account to the Troops of His Serene Highness the Duke of Brunswick. (Folder 38)
  - Pralle (surgeon) 2 DsS, July 20, 1781, Two documents signed by surgeon Pralle, certifying lists of sick men in the Regiment of Maj. Gen. de Rhetz and a detachment of Regiment Prince Frederick, Brunswick Troops.
  - [Brunswick]. Fr[iedrich] Cleve DS, June 26, 1783, 2c. Raport von dem Hochfürstlich Braunschweigischen Corps in American unter Commando des General Major v. Riedesel. Signed by Cleve. (Drawer : Oversize Manuscripts)
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[arl] P[hilipp] Heÿmell, Carl de Wurmb, P[hiliph] H. Murhard, Henri de Bardeleben, W[ilhelm] Freÿenhagen, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 13f. Regiment d'Infanterie du Lieutenant General de Donop, de la Compagnie du Corps, pour 182 Jours, du 25me. Decembre 1781. jusqu'au 24me. Juin 1782 inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Carl Philipp Heÿmell, Maj. Carl de Wurmb, Capt. Philip H. Murhard, Lieut. Henri de Bardeleben, 2nd Lieut. Wilhelm Freÿenhagen, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[arl] P[hilipp] Heÿmell, Carl de Wurmb, J. F[riedrich] Venator, C[arl] E. Henckell, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 13g. Regiment d'Infanterie de Donop de la Compagnie du Major Küzleben pour 182 jours du 25me. Decembre. 1781 jusque au 24me. Juin 1782 inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Carl Philipp Heÿmell, Maj. Carl de Wurmb, Capt. J. Friedrich Venator, ensign Carl E. Henckell, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[arl] P[hilipp] Heÿmell, Carl de Wurmb, Carl de Haussen, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 13h. Regiment d'Infanterie de Donop de la Compagnie du Major de Wurmb pour 182 jours du 25me. Decembre 1781 jusqu'au 24me. Juin 1782/. inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Carl Philipp Heÿmell, Maj. Carl de Wurmb, ensign Carl de Haussen, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[arl] P[hilipp] Heÿmell, Carl de Wurmb, F[ried.] [Wilh.] Geister, [Carl Fried.] de Nagell, F[ried. F.] Murhard, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 13i. Regiment d'Infanterie de Donop de la Compagnie du Colonel Heymel pour 182 Jours du 25me. Decembre 1781 jusqu'au 24me. Juin 1782 inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Carl Philipp Heÿmell, Maj. Carl de Wurmb, Capt. Lieut. Fried. Wilh. Geister, Lieut. Carl Fried. de Nagell, ensign Fried. F. Murhard, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[hristian] V[on] Romrod, E[manuel] de Wilmowsky, J[ohann] L[udolph] Rodemann, E[hrhard] de Drach, C[arl] de Ehrenstein, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 16. Regiment de Lossberg jun. de Hesse de la Compagnie du Major Bauermeister pour 182 jours du 25me. Decembre 1781. jusqu'au 24me. Juin 1782. inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Christian von Romrod, Maj. Emanuel de Wilmowsky, Capt. Lieut. Johann Ludolph Rodemann, 2nd Lieut. Ehrhard de Drach, 2nd Lieut. Carl de Ehrenstein, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[hristian] V[on] Romrod, H[ans] M[oritz] de Biesenrodt, E[manuel] de Wilmowsky, [Carl Henrich] de Toll, M[artin] L[udwig] Wiscker, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 17. Regiment de Lossberg jun. de Hesse de la Compagnie du Lieutenant Colonel de Biesenrodt pour 182 jours du 25me. Decembre 1781 jusq'au 24me. Juin 1782 inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Christian von Romrod, Lieut. Col. Hans Moritz de Biesenrodt, Maj. Emanuel de Wilmowsky, Capt. Lieut. Carl Henrich de Toll, 2nd Lieut. Martin Ludwig Wiscker, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[hristian] V[on] Romrod, E[manuel] de Wilmowsky, J[ohann] M[elchior] Rothe, C[arl Wilhelm] de Bultzingsloewen, C[arl] de Bode, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 18. Regiment de Losberg jun. de Hesse de la Compagne du Corps, pour 182 jours 25me. Decembre 1781 jusq'au 24me. Juin 1782. inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Christian von Romrod, Maj. Emanuel de Wilmowsky, Capt. Lieut. Johann Melchior Rothe, 2nd Lieut. Carl Wilhelm de Bultzingsloewen, ensign Carl de Bode, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[hristian] V[on] Romrod, E[manuel] de Wilmowsky, [Conrad] Schraidt, C[arl Heinrich Friedrich] Lange, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 19. Regiment de Losberg jun. de Hesse de la Compagnie du Colonel de Romrod pour 182 jours du 25me. Decembre 1781 jusqu]au 24me. Juin 1782 inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Christian von Romrod, Maj. Emanuel de Wilmowsky, Capt. Lieut. Conrad Schraidt, ensign Carl Heinrich Friedrich Lange, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. C[hristian] V[on] Romrod, E[manuel] de Wilmowsky, H[ieronimus] Berner, [Friedrich Wilhelm] Fey, and W[illiam] Porter DS, July 5, 1782, 20a. Regiment de Losberg jun. de Hesse, de la Compagnie du Major de Wilmowskÿ pour 182 jours du 25me. Decembre 1781 jusq'au 24me. juin 1782 inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Christian von Romrod, Maj. Emanuel de Wilmowsky, 2nd Lieut. Hieronimus Berner, ensign Friedrich Wilhelm Feÿ, and commissary William Porter.
  - [Hesse-Cassel]. Charles de Kietzell, G. Langenschwartz, C[hristian] Münch, Jean Paul, and G[eorge] Langenschwartz DS, June 24, 1782, 20b. Regiment d'Infanterie du Colonel de Seitz, Compagnie du Colonel de Kietzell pour 182 Jours du 25me. Decembr 1781 Jusqu au 24me. Juin 1782 inclusivement... Muster roll, Dec. 25, 1781-June 24, 1782. Signed by Col. Charles de Kietzell, Maj. G. Langenschwartz, Capt. Lieut. Christian Münch, 2nd Lieut. Jean Paul, and 2nd Lieut. George Langenschwartz.
  - W[illiam] Porter ALS to [William Petty, 1st Marquess of Lansdowne, 2nd Earl of] Shelburne, August 5, 1782, 34. Enclosing a List of the General & Staff Officers of the Hessian Troops, A State of the Foreign Regiments & Detachments at New York, as Mustered to the 24th of June 1782, together with the names, and reasons of absence, of the Officers who did not appear at the Muster. Inclosing [Hesse Cassel. Army]. General and staff officers, 26 July 1782; and Gt. Brit. Army in America. German regiments. State of Foreign Troops at New York … [24 June 1782], with list of officers not present, and 6 individual returns giving the state of the following regiments: Lowenstein, Platte, Donop, Losberg Jun., Bünau, and detachments of regiments in Canada.
  - [William Porter] AD, [between July 13 and August 5, 1782], 34. Names and reasons of absence of the Officers of the Foreign Troops, who were not present at the Muster taken at New York to the 24 June 1782. Enclosed in W[illiam] Porter ALS to the Earl of Shelburne, August 5, 1782.
  - Fr[iedrich Wilhelm von] Losberg DS, July 26, 1782, 34. General and Staff Officers of the Hessian Troops from the 25th. December 1781 to the 24th. June 1782. Enclosed in W[illiam] Porter ALS to the Earl of Shelburne, August 5, 1782.
  - W[illiam] Porter ADS, [July] 1782, 34. State of the Foreign Troops at New York, as Mustered for 182 days from the 25th of December 1781 to the 24 of June 1782... Enclosed in W[illiam] Porter ALS to the Earl of Shelburne, August 5, 1782.
  - W[illiam] Porter ADS, July 3, 1782, 34. State of the Hessian Regiment Bunau for the Muster to the 24 June 1782. Enclosed in W[illiam] Porter ALS to the Earl of Shelburne, August 5, 1782.
  - W[illiam] Porter ADS, July 5, 1782, 34. State of the Hessian Regiment Donop... For the Muster to the 24 June 1782. Enclosed in W[illiam] Porter ALS to the Earl of Shelburne, August 5, 1782.
  - W[illiam] Porter ADS, July 5, 1782, 34. State of the Hessian Regiment Losberg Junior for the Muster to the 24 June 1782. Enclosed in W[illiam] Porter ALS to the Earl of Shelburne, August 5, 1782.
  - W[illiam] Porter ADS, July 4, 1782, 34. State of the Battallion of Hessian Grenadiers Commanded by Colonel de Lowenstein for the Muster to the 24 June 1782. Enclosed in W[illiam] Porter ALS to the Earl of Shelburne, August 5, 1782.
  - W[illiam] Porter ADS, July 4, 1782, 34. State of the Battallion of Hessian Grenadiers Commanded by Major Platte (late Graffs) to the 24 June 1782. Enclosed in W[illiam] Porter ALS to the Earl of Shelburne, August 5, 1782.
  - W[illiam] Porter ADS, July 12, 1782, 34. State of the Detachments at New York of the Foreign Regiments in Canada for the Muster from 25 Decem. 1781 to the 24 June 1782... Enclosed in W[illiam] Porter ALS to the Earl of Shelburne, August 5, 1782.
Related collections held by the Clements Library include the following Revolutionary War collections that deal specifically with Hessian involvement:
Loftus Cliffe papers
Henry Clinton papers
Benjamin Gilbert letterbook
Nathanael Greene papers
Freiherr von Jungkenn papers
Frederick Mackenzie papers
J.R. (Hessian) Journal
Auerbach, Inge. Die Hessen in Amerika 1776-1783. Darmstadt: Hessische Historische Kommission Darmstadt, 1996.
Mackenzie, Frederick, and Allen French. A British fusilier in revolutionary Boston: being the diary of Lieutenant Frederick Mackenzie, adjutant of the Royal Welch fusiliers, January 5-April 30, 1775, with a letter describing his voyage to America. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1926.